Guide to the Harvey Williams Cushing Papers in the Yale University Library
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Papers held in the Medical Historical Library, Part II
  - Writings, 1898-1940; Series III
    - Additional printed copies of Cushing's writings
      - 274. The Medical Career (three copies: first is first edition, a duplicate of this is in reprint volume XVI without outer binding; second and third copies are identical copies of the second edition.)
      - 307. "Dyspituitarism": Twenty Years Later (two copies: first is as printed in Archives of Internal Medicine; second copy is in The Harvey Lectures, 1932-1933.
      - 316. The Pioneer Medical Schools of Central New York (duplicate of same in reprint volume XVIII except this copy has green cover)
      - 325. Ercole Lelli and Écorché in Proceedings of the Charaka Club
      - Not in bibliography. Harvey Cushing Selected Papers on Neurosurgery
      - Not in bibliography. Studies in Acromegaly, 1925-1931 (collected reprints by Cushing and others which were never published as a monograph)
  - Family Papers, 1780-1944; Series IV
    This series is composed of published volumes written by or about family members. The series also includes a few books owned by family members. The volumes are listed in the order in which they are shelved. No material in this series is included in the microfilm.
    - Fitch, Roscoe Conkling. History of the Fitch Family, A.D. 1400-1930, two volumes (Haverhill Mass.)
    - Williams, John Oliver. A Genealogy of Williams Families (Brookline)., 1938
    - Cushing, Lemuel. The Genealogy of the Cushing Family (Montreal). two copies, 1877
    - Dame, George W. Sketch of the Life and Character of Jonathan P. Cushing, M.A., President of Hampton Sydney College from American Quarterly Register, 11:113-28., 1838
    - Robbins, Mrs. Mary Caroline (Pike). The Rescue of an Old Place (Boston)., 1900
    - Cushing, James Stevenson. The Genealogy of the Cushing Family (Montreal). two copies, 1905
    - Cushing, Caleb. The Treaty of Washington (New York)., 1873
    - Cushing, Caleb. An Oration Pronounced before the Literary Societies of Amherst College, Aug. 23, 1836 (Boston).
    - Edward Fitch Cushing Memorial (Cleveland). three copies, 1911
    - Daughters of the American Revolution. Massachusetts. Old Colony Chapter, Hingham. Hingham: A Story of Its Early Settlement (Hingham)., 1911
    - Crehore, Albert Cushing. Autobiography. (Gates Mills, Ohio)., 1944
    - Bell, Mrs. Margaret Van Horn (Dwight). A Journey to Ohio in 1810, ed. M. Farrand (New Haven)., 1920
    - Dittrick, Howard, comp. Pioneer Medicine in the Western Reserve. (Cleveland)., 1932
    - Raynor, Mrs. Ellen M. History of the Town of Cheshire, Berkshire County, Mass., E. L. Petitclerc jy. auth. (Holyoke)., 1885
    - Elliott, John, and Samuel Johnson, Jr. Dictionary; second edition (Suffield)., 1800
    - Ross, Robert. The American Latin Grammar or a Compleat Introduction to the Latin Tongue, 5th ed. (Providence)., 1780
    - Freeman, Samuel. The Town Officer or the Power and Duty of Selectmen as Contained in the Laws of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 6th ed. (Boston)., 1805
    - White, Henry Kirke. The Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham, ed. R. Southey, volume one (New York)., 1820
    - Walker, John. A Critical Pronouncing Dictionary; first pocket edition (Hartford)., 1823
    - Walker, John. Elegant Extracts of Poetry (Hartford)., 1823
    - Wilson, Ella Grant. Famous Old Euclid Avenue of Cleveland Ohio., 1932
    - Crouse, David Eldridge. The Ohio Gateway (New York)., 1938
  - Writings of Others Concerning Cushing, 1910-1988; Series VI
    This series is composed of published articles, books, and other printed matter about Harvey Cushing or dedicated to him. These writings are arranged in chronological order by date of publication. None of the material in this series is included on the microfilm.
    - Starr, M. Allen. Tumors of the Acoustic Nerve...after Operations by Dr. Harvey Cushing (reprint from the American Journal of the Medical Sciences ), 1910
    - Vanguard, pp. 1-162 (seven issues), 1917-1918, 1941
    - Base Hospital No. 5: Concerning Base Hospital No. 5 (two copies), 1920
    - Cushing birthday volume, April 8, 1929 (from Arch. Surg., 18:xxi, 935-2046)
    - Boyd, Walter Willard. Dr. Harvey Cushing: A Book of Photographs, 1928-1932. (four copies)
    - Pendray, Edward. Man of Brains (from Today, June 27, 1936, bound and unbound copies)
    - Bibliotheca Medica, L'Art Ancien S.A. Catalogue XXI dedicated to Harvey Cushing, 1938
    - Vincent, Clovis. Leçon Inaugurale, Chaire de Neuro-Chirurgie, Faculté de Medecine de Paris, 1939 January 26
    - Harvey Cushing Society. Harvey Cushing's Seventieth Birthday Party, April 8, 1939. Speeches, letters, and tributes (Springfield, Ill.)
    - Schuman's booksellers. Seventy Noteworthy Medical Rarities in Honor of the 70th Birthday of Dr. Harvey Cushing, Together with a Tribute by Dr. Lawrence Reynolds (New York) (four copies: one hard bound with HC's name engraved, in slip case; three paper bound copies), 1939
    - Acta Chirugica Scandinavica. To Harvey Cushing on his 70th birthday from Scandinavian friends and colleagues. Acta Chir. Scand, 82:99-363 (two copies: one hardbound in slip case, one paper bound), 1939
    - Zentralblatt fur Neurochirurgie. Harvey Cushing zum 70. Geburtstag. Zbl. Neurochir, 4: 195-272, 1939
    - Henderson, William Robert. The Pituitary Adenomata: a follow-up study of the surgical results in 338 cases (Dr. Harvey Cushing's series) Brit. J. Surg ., 26:811-921. Preceded by tribute to H. C. (two copies: one hard bound, one paper bound), 1939
    - Yale Journal of Biology. Cushing anniversary number. Yale J. Biol. Med., 11:409-580, 1939
    - Harvey Cushing 1969-1939: Appreciations. (in two volumes and one slip case)
    - Bulletin of the Los Angeles Neurological Society, Harvey Cushing Memorial Number, vol. 5, no. 1., 1940 April 8
    - The Life of Harvey Cushing, Human Adventure, 38th chapter. A CBS program in conjuntion with the University of Chicago, broadcast 1940 Aug 31
      See: Historical Sound Recordings, Sterling Memorial Library
    - Sharpe, Wiiliam. Brain Surgeon (Viking Press, NY), 1952
    - Rubin, J. L. Harvey Cushing and England, Broadway, 1964 March
    - Niehans, Paul. Cellular Therapy from the Viewpoint of the Doctor and Patient, O H Verlag Thun (Switzerland), 1964
    - Journal of Neurosurgery, Harvey Cushing Centennial Edition (four copies), 1969
    - Classics in Surgery No. 6: Harvey Cushing, (Schering Corporation), 1973
    - Reich, Stephen. Harvey Cushing's Guillain-Barre Syndrome: An Historical Diagnosis, Neurosurgery, vol 21, no.2, 1987
    - Journal of Neurosurgery, The Tradition of Harvey Cushing Commemorated by a Stamp in the Great American Stamp Series, vol 67, no 5. (magazine and three reprints), 1987 November
    - Lakartindningen, Mannen bakin syndromet: Harvey Cushing (two copies), 1988 April
- Additional material held in Manuscripts and Archives, Addition 1
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1906-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Francis, William w., 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Special files
    - Garrison's History of Medicine (revision), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Honorary degress, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Meningiomas [pages from Louise Eisenhardt's little black book], Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Personal calendars, 1920-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8-17)
    - World War I [poster of Les Gosses dans les Ruines by Paul Gsell and Poulbot], Circa 1916-1918 (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - "Harvey (Williams) Cushing" [personal record for Yale classbook], Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "The XIIIth International Physiological Congress", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Additional material held in Manuscripts and Archives, Accession 2018-M-002
  - Letters to Mr. A. R. Hobart, 1939, undated (Box 1)
    Four letters, 1939 and undated, written by Harvey Williams Cushing to Mr. A. R. Hobart.